.
>> good afternoon.
Welcome to the MARCH 4th 2025
regular meeting of the san
francisco board of supervisors.
MADAM Clerk, will you please
call the roll?
>> thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
Supervisor chin chen present
supervisor chen chen present
supervisor dorsey dorsey
present supervisor and engardio
and engardio present supervisor
fielder fielder not present
supervisor mahmood who at
present supervisor randleman
present mandel men present
supervisor melgar male guard
present supervisor sadr sadr
present supervisor sherril
sharon present and supervisor
walton walton present MR.
PRESIDENT you have a quorum.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk.
Supervisor fielder is stuck
in jury duty so can we have a
motion to excuse?
Supervisor fielder moved by
sherril is there a second
second by chen and I think I'm
going to say excuse her until
she arrives.
If she arrives and we can take
that without objection.
>> okay.
All right.
>> the san francisco board of
supervisors acknowledges that
we are on the unceded ancestral
homeland of the romita aloni
who are the original
inhabitants of the san
francisco peninsula as the
indigenous stewards of this
land and in accordance with
their traditions the romita
colony have never ceded lost
nor forgotten their
responsibilities as the
caretakers of this place as
well as for all peoples who
reside in their traditional
territory as guests we
recognize that we benefit from
living and working on their
traditional homelands.
We wish to pay our respects by
acknowledging the ancestors,
elders and relatives of the
dramatist aloni community and
by affirming their rights as
first peoples and colleagues.
Will you join me in saying the
pledge of allegiance?
I pledge allegiance to the flag
of the united states of america
and to the republic for which
it stands one nation under GOD,
indivisible, with liberty and
justice for all.
And on behalf of the board I
would like to acknowledge the
staff at S.F. Gov tv
particularly today kaleena
mendoza who record each of our
meetings and make the
transcripts available to the
public online.
MADAM Clerk, are there any
communications?
>> yes.
Thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
The san francisco board of
supervisors welcomes you to
attend this meeting in person
in the board's legislative
chamber room two 52nd floor
in city hall or you MAY watch
the proceeding on as of g of
tv's channel 26.
You MAY also view the
livestream at ww w dot S.F. G o
vtv.Org if you'd like to
provide comment in writing you
can do so by sending an email
to boost S.F. Gov dot org or
use the postal service.
>> send the letter to the san
francisco board of supervisors
the number one DR. Carlton
should be good place city hall
room 244 san francisco
california 94102 if you need to
make a reasonable accommodation
request under the americans
with disabilities act or to
request language assistance,
contact the clerk's office at
least two business days
in advance by calling
(415) 554-5184.
Thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk.
Let's go to approval of the
meeting minutes.
>> approval of the JANUARY 28th
2025 board meeting minutes.
>> colleagues, we are approving
the meeting minutes from the
JANUARY 28th 2025 regular board
meeting.
Are there any changes to these
meeting minutes?
I don't see any of them.
Is there a motion to approve
move by walton?
Is there a second seconded by
melgar?
And MADAM Clerk, will you
please call the roll on the
minutes supervisor mandolin I
mandolin eyes supervisor melgar
melgar I supervisor sadr sadr I
supervisor sherril sherril I
supervisor walton walton I
supervisor chin chin I
supervisor dorsey dorsey I
supervisor engardio and
engardio I and supervisor
mahmood mahmood I there are ten
eyes then without objection the
minutes will be approved after
public comment as presented
MADAM Clerk let's go to our
consent agenda items one
through 16 items one through 16
are on consent.
>> these items are considered
to be routine unless a member
objects and would like an item
to be removed and considered
separately.
>> and colleagues does anyone
want to sever any items from
the consent agenda?
I don't see anyone see no one
on the roster.
>> MADAM Clerk, can you please
call the roll on items one
through 16 supervisor mandolin
hi randleman I supervisor
melgar melgar I supervisor
sauder sorter I supervisor
sherril sherril I supervisor
walton walton and I supervisor
chan chin I supervisor chen
chin I supervisor dorsey dorsey
I supervisor engardio and
engardio I and supervisor
mahmood mahmood I there are ten
eyes without objection the
ordinances are passed on first
reading and finally passed and
resolutions are adopted MADAM
Clerk can you take us to our
regular agenda unfinished
business item 17 item 17 this
is an ordinance to amend the
planning code to exempt certain
types of projects in the
downtown area that replace non
residential uses with
residential uses from
development impact fees and
requirements to include the
inclusionary housing fee.
Remove the application deadline
from the commercial to
residential adaptive reuse
program and to require periodic
reporting to the inclusionary
housing technical advisory
committee and to affirm the
second determination and to
make the appropriate findings.
>> MADAM Clerk, please call the
roll on item 17 supervisor
randleman hi mandolin I
supervised for melgar melgar by
supervisor sartor sadr I
supervisor sherril sherril I
supervisor walton walton no
supervisor chen chin I
supervisor chin chin eyes
supervisor dorsey dorsey I
supervisor engardio engardio I
and supervisor mahmood mahmood
I there are nine eyes and one
no with supervisor walton
voting no the ordinance is
finally passed MADAM Clerk will
you please call item number 18
item 18 this is an ordinance to
retrofit actively authorize the
department of public library to
accept and expend an
approximate $1.9 million grant
award from the andrew w mellon
foundation for the jail and
reentry services program term
NOVEMBER 1st, 2024 through
DECEMBER 31st, 2027 and to
amend the annual salary
ordinance for fiscal years 2024
through 25 and 2526 to provide
for the addition of three
positions one grant funded full
time position class 3630
library and one one grant
funded full time position
in class 1822 and add mental
analyst and one grant funded
full time position an 1823
senior administrative analyst
at the public library through
JUNE 30th 2026 please call the
roll in this item on item 18
supervisor mandolin hi
randleman I supervisor melgar
melgar I supervisor sartor sadr
I supervisor sherril sherril I
supervisor walton walton I
supervisor chin chin I
supervisor dorsey dorsey I
supervisor and engardio and
engardio I and supervisor
mahmood mahmood I there are ten
eyes without objection this
ordinance is passed on first
reading MADAM Clerk can you
please call items 19 and 20
together items 19 and 20 are
two resolutions that authorize
the recreation and parks
department to accept and expend
grants.
Item 19 enters into an
agreement with b p embarcadero
plaza lp the downtown san
francisco partnership and the
office of economic and
workforce development
pertaining to potential
improvements and renovations at
the embarcadero plaza, the sue
beerman park and to accept cash
and in-kind grants from xp of
approximately 2.5 million for
design and art project
management services and to
accept potential additional
grants of approximately 10
million which could include
cash grants from the downtown
community benefit district or
in-kind grants of construction
services from b xp for the term
through DECEMBER 2028 seeing no
one on the roster MADAM Clerk
let's take these items same
house, same call without
objection these MR. PRESIDENT I
apologize I'll just before you
gavel down I will say item 20
this is a resolution that
accepts an expensive grant
retroactively from the
california state coastal
conservancy for the great
highway promenade planning
project in the amount of 1
million.
>> all right, now let's take
that out now let's take these
items same house, same call.
>> without objection these
resolutions are adopted.
Now let's go to item number 21.
>> item 21.
This is a resolution to approve
and authorize the general
manager of the san francisco
public utilities commission to
execute the first amendment to
a contract for engineering
services for an all valley
water treatment plant as a
nation with cdr smith inc to
increase the contract amount by
9.6 million for a total
contract amount of 24.6 million
and to increase the contract
duration by four years for a
new term of ten years through
FEBRUARY 2030.
And let's take this item same
house, same call without
objection the resolution is
adopted.
And let's go to item 22.
>> item 22.
This is a resolution to
retroactively authorize the
office of economic and
workforce development to accept
and expend a $675,000 grant
from the james irvine
foundation for the northern
california apprenticeship
network sustainability grant
for the term through OCTOBER
11th, 2027.
>> and we'll take this item
same house, same call without
objection the resolution is
adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk please call her
next item item 23 this is a
resolution to approve and
authorize the director of the
mayor's office of housing and
community development to
execute loan documents for the
permanent financing of 1135
1155 and 1175 illustrate with
1155 lsb llc pursuant to the
small science program and the
preservation and seismic safety
program for a loan amount of
50.6 million and to confirm the
second determination and let's
take this item same house, same
call without objection the
resolution is adopted.
MADAM Clerk, let's go to our
next item item 24.
>> this is a resolution to
authorize the department of hhs
the homelessness and support of
housing to execute a standards
agreement with the california
department of housing and
community development having
anticipated revenue to the city
in an amount of approximately
8.2 million of project homekey
grant funds to retroactively
accept and expend these funds
for the acquisition of the
property located at 42 oda
street for permanent supportive
housing and to support its
operations for costs incurred
MARCH third, 2021 through JUNE
30th 2026 and to approve and
authorize sage to commit
approximately 8.7 million
in matching funds for
acquisition of the property and
a ten year minimum of operation
subsidies to affirm the secret
determination and to make the
appropriate findings.
And we'll take this item same
house, same call without
objection the resolution is
adopted.
MADAM Clerk, please call item
25.
>> item 20 five is a resolution
to approve an agreement between
the city and new flier of
america inc to procure for 40
foot and three 60 foot battery
electric busses along with
spare parts special tools,
manuals for training and
telematics licenses through a
cooperative purchasing
agreement established by the
state of washington for 13.4
million and a five year term.
>> and we can take this item
same house, same call without
objection the resolution is
adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk, can you please
call our next item item 26.
>> this item was referred
without recommendation from the
budget and finance committee.
It's a resolution to approve
the third amendment to the
grant agreement between the
city and brilliant corners to
administer the flexible housing
subsidy pool program to
increase the agreement amount
by approximately 19.3 million
for a new total amount of
approximately 59.54 million to
extend the grant term by 12
months JUNE 30th 2025 for a
total term through JUNE 30th
2026.
>> supervisor dorsey thank you
PRESIDENT Mandela and
colleagues I wanted to provide
additional context on why we
referred this item out without
recommend.
Dacian at last week's budget
and finance committee we had a
robust discussion about this
contract with the department
and my committee colleagues
chair chan and supervisor and
gado for background brilliant
corners provides housing
location coordination subsidy
administration and landlord
liaison services to support
scattered site permanent
supportive housing for up to
500 adults in private rental
units.
however, it has consistently
struggled to meet its 75 day
placement target averaging 140
days instead.
And despite serving more
clients it has also
significantly underspent
millions in funds allocated
over the past three fiscal
years due to staffing shortages
and slow placements.
Now some of this contractual
underperform commences
attributable to the contractor.
However, it also appears that
some underperformance issues
are also attributable to the
department at least in terms of
setting goals and objectives
that were apparently never
realistic for these types of
services.
But either way I think this is
unhelpful to us in our role as
supervisors to make prudent
budgetary and policy decisions.
As of last week we are informed
that brilliant corners is at
full capacity for enrollments
with 90 households actively
searching for housing.
Importantly hca is also in the
process of re procuring this
agreement for this this spring
of 2025.
As we discussed during the
committee meeting, they will be
standardizing agreements to
maintain consistency across all
flexible housing subsidy pools,
providers including adjusting
the timelines for housing
placement.
Although this contract was
moved out of committee without
recommendation I will be voting
for it to approve it today
given the forthcoming
procurement process as well as
the near-term progress we have
seen since the committee
meeting.
However, I did want to flag
this as an item of concern for
me borrowing a page from the
playbook of budget chair connie
chan who I always appreciated
for occasionally highlighting
similarly worthy matters that
are attention worthy of
attention for the full board.
>> I think this did merit
further explanation.
Supervisor chan thank you
PRESIDENT Benjamin.
I just want to express that my
sentiment and concur what was
expressed by supervisor dorsey
,our vice chair on the
committee I regretfully want is
to say that I think the
committee actually has a chair
sentiment and that we have a
consensus of how we're going to
approach items like as such.
So colleagues, I urge you to to
evaluate in.
Feel free to ask any of the
member of the committee
questions should you see any
items that come out with our
recommendation?
It really is actually still a
indication that we are
in consensus as this item is
coming out with that
recommendation.
>> I hope that you will see
less of it but regrettably I
don't think that's the case
because we are going to be
tougher and tougher days ahead.
Thank you.
>> supervisor sherril I want to
add my voice to my colleagues
supervisors dorsey and chan
whose remarks I will not repeat
but I wish to echo these
contractors require adequate
resources and support to be
successful but there must also
be clear accountability when
agreed upon performance metrics
are not met or one of agreed
upon performance metrics are
not realistic.
Supervisor dorsey mentioned
very clearly that this contract
has a 75 day target when
in fact the results are closer
to 140.
Based on my personal work
in the past I know that those
results are driven almost
entirely by the fact that
individuals who do not actually
get placed are languishing
longer and longer.
In my mind it is difficult to
appropriately judge contracts
where we have performance
metrics that are in some ways
impossible to meet and which do
not look entirely at the
population they are looking to
serve.
Many people do in fact get
housed before that 75 day wait.
Many people never get housing.
They drive these average
numbers up.
Does that mean the brilliant
corners is doing a good job?
Does that mean they're doing a
bad job?
It is almost impossible to see
because of the lack of
thoughtfulness in putting
together some of the
performance metrics in these
contracts.
We need to have an in-depth
conversation on all contracts
both new and soon to be renewed
and amended going forward.
And I want to thank my
colleagues on the budget
committee for their
thoughtfulness in bringing this
to a head here today.
>> thank you.
Supervisor sherril thank you
supervisors for your comments.
It sounds like we can take this
item same house, same call
without objection the
resolution is adopted.
And MADAM Clerk can you please
call item 27 and I'm 27.
>> this is a resolution to
affirm san francisco's
commitment to birthright
citizenship as a constitutional
right and to oppose PRESIDENT
Donald trump's executive order
that attempts to
unconstitutionally limit
birthright citizenship.
>> and we can take this item
same house, same call without
objection, the resolution is
adopted.
MADAM Clerk, can you please
call item 28 item 28 this is a
resolution to authorize
fundraising for services
related to immigration lgbtq
rights, environmental
protection, reproductive rights
and racial equity.
>> notwithstanding the behest
id payment waiver and I think
we can take this item same
house, same call without
objection this resolution is
adopted.
MADAME Clerk, can you please
call our next item item 29 this
is a resolution to support the
S.F. Mta the san francisco
municipal transports and
agency's joint development
program goals and policy to set
a citywide policy on the joint
development of transit and
housing projects to address the
S.F. Mta's budget deficit and
advance san francisco's housing
and equity goals.
>> supervisor melgar thank you
so much colleagues.
>> this is a resolution
supporting the policy that the
mta has developed and passed
recently.
As we all know muni is facing a
$321 million structural deficit
every year in the next couple
of years threatening service
cuts, fare hikes and the loss
of essential programs like
school crossing guards.
>> this structural deficit is
due almost entirely because of
the loss of parking revenue.
>> over the past decade people
have been driving their own
cars less parking in mta
parking lots less and taking
uber, lyft waymo's more.
The pandemic has accelerated
this trend but it did not start
it.
>> the joint development
program goals and policy
unlocks new income streams
possibly for the agency in the
future by developing the real
estate assets the agency owns
for revenue generating uses are
new underutilized S.F. Mta
owned land without burdening
taxpayers.
This means more of the things
we need like housing,
affordable housing services for
riders, shops, a stronger
transit system and a boost to
our local economy.
Major cities around the world
have all done this.
Anyone who has ever visited
grand central station knows
that riders can drop off their
dry cleaning, pick up their
dinner, do any number of things
that interact economically with
the train station and it is
really wonderful.
>> the S.F. Mta owns dozens of
properties across san francisco
including stations century old
backyards, parking garages
in lots.
These properties are valuable
assets that can serve more than
one purpose.
Under this framework we can
develop housing on S.F. Empty
on land helping us meet our
housing goals while securing a
stable revenue stream for
public transit.
It's a win win and it will help
our city's economic recovery.
By doing this we ensure that
muni can continue to serve the
public without resorting to
fare increases or service
reductions.
Remaining the vibrant,
accessible, affordable system
that it always has been.
And just as importantly we can
activate land to create vibrant
transit oriented communities.
Thank you supervisors at
soldering engardio dorsi and
mahmood for your early support.
I want to also thank my
committee vice chair for the
land use committee supervisor
cheyenne chen for her
assistance and the in her her
amendments to the resolution.
Thank you so much and I hope to
get your support.
Thank you.
Much for seeing no more names
on the roster can we take this
item same house, same call.
Without objection the
resolution is adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk, can you please
call our next item item 30 this
is an ordinance to amend the
campaign and governmental
conduct code to update the
conflict of interest codes form
700 filing requirements all
rights.
I think we can take this item
same house, same call.
>> without objection the
ordinance is passed on first
reading.
>> and MADAM Clerk can you
please call item 31?
Item 31 this is an ordinance to
amend the administrative code
to authorize the tax collector
to refund property taxes to the
assessee or latest record owner
of the property if the amount
of the refund is less than
10,000 and there has been no
transfer of the property during
or since the fiscal year for
which the taxes to be refunded
were levied on a 31 we can take
this item.
Same house, same call without
objection the ordinance is
passed on first reading.
Supervisor jan present
amendment and colleagues my
apologies I have overlooked my
vote and if I could request
that you MAY indulge me to
allow me to rescind our vote
for item 28 which I can explain
further whenever PRESIDENT
Vandeman see fit.
>> okay.
Do we need a motion in the
second to rescind a vote or we
just he motion to reconsider
recess that was moved by chan
seconded by walton.
We can take that without
objection.
>> yes.
All right.
So the the vote is rescinded
and then supervisor jia thank
you, PRESIDENT Domain.
Colleagues, I am going to be
voting against item number 28
for the reason previously I
voted in support for for this
waiver granting to our mayor
and city attorney but I am
voting against this particular
waiver for assessor recorder.
First and foremost assessor
recorder walk him towards has
been a great elected but also
formerly as our great city
staff has done really
tremendous work during the
pandemic related to same costs
as a mayoral staff during a
very critical time.
I don't.
Now does view his role as
assessor recorder again very
different role as a
independently elected and in a
process that is critical time
as always but more than ever
that he will oversee he and his
team will be overseeing a lot
of.
Potentially a lot of appeals
from corporation and other
entities through the appeal
process involving property tax
and related matters.
So with that I feel
uncomfortable to see that he
receive and he and his team to
receive.
Pavement waiver that I think
there's even though there's I
do not think that in any way
there's no allegation of
inappropriateness just a
perception of it and with that
I will be voting no against
item number 28.
>> all right, MADAM Clerk,
please call the roll on item 28
an item 28 supervisor.
>> randleman high and I
supervisor melgar melgar I
supervisor sardar sartor I
supervisor sherril sherril I
supervisor wilton wilton eyes
supervisor chin no chin no
supervisor chin chin eyes
supervisor dorsey dorsey eyes
supervisor and audio and video
I and supervisor mahmood
mahmood I.
There are nine eyes and one no
with supervisor chan voting no
all right the resolution is
adopted and then MADAM Clerk do
we need to revote on 29 since
we took that same house same
call?
>> or how do we do that?
MR. PRESIDENT, can you repeat
that question?
My apologies.
So we had taken I think we had
taken 29 same house, same call
.
Do we need to revote on that or
no?
No, we do not.
Great.
>> can you call item 32?
>> item 32 this is an ordinance
to amend the business and tax
regulations code to remove the
requirement that parking
operators certify and report
periodically to the city the
ratio of their unaccounted
parking tickets to total issued
tickets for each parking
station for the reporting
period.
>> MADAM Clerk, please call the
roll on item 32 supervisor
mandolin hi mandolin eyes
supervisor melgar melgar I
supervisor sartor sartor I
supervisor sherril sherril I
supervisor walton walton I
supervisor chin chin eyes
supervisor dorsey dorsey eyes
supervisor engardio and
engardio I.
And supervisor muhammad mahmood
I there are ten eyes without
objection this ordinance is
passed on first reading madam
clerk please call our next item
item 33 this is a motion to
reappoint clinton laufman to
the citizen's committee on
community development term
ending FEBRUARY 23rd 27.
>> all right, let's take this
item same house, same call.
Without objection the motion is
approved and MADAM Clerk, can
you please call item 31?
>> item 30 four this is a
motion to reappoint cindy f
lopez chastain to the early
childhood community oversight
and advisory committee term
ending OCTOBER 8th, 2026.
>> let's take this item same
house, same call without
objection the motion is
approved and MADAM Clerk let's
go to our 230 special order.
>> recognition of
commendations.
Yes.
The recognition of
commendations for meritorious
service to the city and county
of san francisco supervisor
sartor thank you PRESIDENT
Benjamin.
Colleagues today I rise to
celebrate samuel a treasured
cornerstone of san francisco's
chinatown for over 100 years I
think we all know there are
restaurants in san francisco
that are more than just
restaurants and samuel is one
of those.
It represents the preservation
of cultural heritage.
Serves as a bridge connecting
many generations in our city
through authentic chinese
cuisine.
Many of you MAY be familiar
with the renowned barbecue pork
rice rolls with hot mustard and
many of you probably have spent
some late nights at samuel.
During 2020 I had the honor of
collaborating with samuel
through our north beach
deliveries initiative where we
distributed meals to those
sheltering in place during the
pandemic.
Samuel has been a second home
and a community gathering space
to so many throughout our city
.
This has all been made possible
because of the longtime chef
david how I want to extend my
deepest gratitude to david for
his remarkable over 40 years of
service to our community.
He leaves a legacy of hard work
of hospitality and dedication
to a craft a very delicious
craft.
Joining him today are his
family and his friends jason
fong excuse me jane fong, jason
julie and stephen lee, our
former entertainment
commissioner and now port
commissioner.
And I would like to invite
stephen first to make remarks.
Afternoon supervisors welcome
new supervisors.
I just want to say samuel has
been a mainstay for us all the
way in college.
I remember going there that's
all the rudest waiter in the
world.
>> MR. Holt took over after
that so passed away I had a
chance to be with the whole
family back in 2012 when the
restaurant was shut down.
I helped the stave it.
>> at that time and I had the
chance to work with MR. Hall
and I'd have to say the reason
why I support a lot of the
small businesses in chinatown
and the hard working mom and
pops is because of this man
right here.
This guy works 12 hours a day.
He doesn't stop.
He loves the legacy of sam wall
and what it means to the
community and this is why we
support him.
I met julie and jason.
Julie worked there at nine
years old after school and
jason with their team same
time.
So during covid when we had the
shutdown and at that time we
were running three shifts at
sam wall we were still doing
the late night dining to in the
morning but when covid hit we
had to lay everybody off and we
were stuck either losing the
restaurant again or doing
takeout or what we did later
thanks to the board and the
nonprofits to help feed those
seniors that couldn't go out.
MR..
Hall actually was supervisor
then of other what, three
shifts and he didn't have to do
a whole lot then but then he
came back and worked 12 hours
again for two years because
pandemic lasted too long and we
as investors who helped save
town will again we really are
proud and dedicated and thank
you MR. Hall and the family.
>> it is sad that he has to
retire and that we're stuck
looking for a new chef.
Hopefully.
>> but I want to introduce
jason hall to julie who is also
a nurse and of course MR. Hall,
a good friend of okay.
Okay.
Go ahead.
Thank you supervisors.
all right.
And I have the second
commendation here.
I'd like to invite rob connolly
to come up and I would note
that we have been joined by our
former city attorney and
general manager dennis herrera
as well as our former police
chief greg sir and I think they
MAY be here for rob.
>> so as I was as I was handing
out the the certificates to get
my colleagues to sign today,
they got worried that you might
be retiring.
>> that is not what is going on
here.
Rob connolly is not retiring
but it is the 25th anniversary
year since he joined the boys
and girls club of san francisco
or bgc S.F. Where he is
PRESIDENT Rob received his B.A.
From yale university and
attended oxford university as a
visiting study fellow.
He began working for the boys
and girls clubs in 1998,
serving two years with the boys
and girls clubs of america's
relations team in washington dc
and then he joined the
organization's san francisco
chapter as executive director a
quarter century ago and then
was named PRESIDENT In 2005
during his time with the boys
and girls clubs of san
francisco, rob has focused
primarily on expanding the
reach of the clubs to serve
more youth and more communities
while modernizing the programs
and services they provide.
He is a prodigious and constant
fundraiser for the organization
bringing in the money they need
to attract and retain top
talent and renovate facilities
to ensure that youth have safe
spaces where they can learn,
grow and succeed.
He and his team have developed
and implemented programs and
services that measurably
improve the lives of young
people focusing on academic
success, healthy lifestyles,
good character and community
engagement and job readiness
with earning potential as
PRESIDENT Rob currently
oversees bgc S.F. Eight
traditional clubhouses, five
school based clubs and camp
mendocino, a 2000 acre
residential summer camp in the
redwoods of northern california
.
He manages an operation of over
300 staff members under his
leadership the clubs have
raised up ten winners and six
runners up for the esteemed
national program excellence
award.
16 club youth have also reached
the state finals for california
youth of the year three three
were named california youth of
the year and one was named
national youth of the year
in 2021 rob was recognized with
horizon award for his
outstanding contributions to
the growth and development of
the clubs in the pacific region
.
Last year he was recognized
with the masters and mentors
award one of the club's highest
honors.
Rob played the lead staff role
in raising more than $60
million through the club's
brighter futures capital
campaign and in 2018 under his
leadership the boys and girls
clubs of san francisco also
launched a $50 million capacity
building campaign and they've
raised 49 million.
So almost there.
>> each campaign included new
clubhouses, important upgrades
at existing clubhouses and at
camp mendocino and an
investment in competitive
compensate asian rob is the
former board PRESIDENT And
current board vice PRESIDENT
For the california alliance of
boys and girls clubs which
advocates for funding and
public policies that support
the success of clubs in urban,
suburban and rural communities
around california.
I want to thank you rob, for
your service to our youth and
our city and to wish you a very
happy 20th anniversary of the
boys and girls clubs of san
francisco and my colleagues are
lining up to sing your praises
so supervisor welcome.
>> thank you so much, PRESIDENT
Melman and I'm going to be
brief but rob one I just want
to thank you for your decades
of leadership of our clubs.
Most of our young people within
community have gone through the
doors of boys and girls clubs
and one way or another whether
as has been as members or as
young people that you have
employed.
And so I want to thank you for
continue ing to focus on
leading our young people to
success even so many years
later you could go on to do so
many different things but I
appreciate the fact that you
stay there steadfast within our
communities and I just want to
mention before our schools had
the innumerable amount of
afterschool programs that they
have now located on our
campuses, there was the boys
and girls club there from the
very beginning.
And so I appreciate your
steadfast, steadfast and
committed leadership and of
course just looking forward to
to continue work with our young
people through boys and girls
clubs.
>> thank you.
Thank you.
Supervisor one supervisor
dorsey thank you PRESIDENT
Randleman and I just I was
actually the supervisor when I
saw that there we were signing
something for you.
I just thought oh no, no I
please I'm not retiring and I'm
glad that that that you are you
are not the only one.
>> the other the other thing
when I when dennis herrera's
name was mentioned and I didn't
see him here I thought I might
have to step into the role that
I'm familiar with of being
spokesman for dennis herrera.
But apparently I didn't I don't
have to do that because he is
here.
I just want to express my
appreciation for the work that
you did when I was in that
office we had a case that the
aimco case where we were able
to after a lot of contention
find a win win that was great
for all the parties.
But the boys and girls club
were such a part of that and it
became the willie mays
clubhouse and it was just an
honor for me even 20 years ago
I remember how proud I was and
how proud the office was to be
a part of that because of your
leadership.
So thanks so much.
Thank you.
Supervisor dorsey supervisor
melgar thank you.
I was also one of the folks who
was just like oh no worries me
going so I'm glad we're just
celebrating your time.
So before I was elected
supervisor I was the executive
director of the jamestown
community center and
collaborated with your staff
and I have to say two things
about your leadership that are
so amazing and important.
One is a culture of
collaborative ness that you
have instilled with everyone
in the agency so we had
tournaments for girls got goals
inside your gyms.
We had all kinds of you know,
trainings for youth develop
ment and trauma enforced
practices and everything.
It was just such a wonderful
thing to see all of the people
in the community working
together for the young people
in our community and doing it
with collaboration and love.
So that is something that comes
from the top in you have like
created that culture and I am
so thankful.
And the other thing that I
always admired was the amazing
training that your staff had.
So it was always that full and
intentional, culturally
competent and deeply community
rooted and for that I also
thank you so much and I'm glad
you're not going anywhere so
congratulations.
So well-deserved to have this
recognition.
>> oh, all right, rob, it's
your turn.
This one and that one.
This one.
All right.
>> well, supervisor thank you.
That was super kind of of all
of you supervisor amanda and
thank you for thinking of doing
this does sound like it's
something that happens when you
retire so now I'm not quite
going anywhere yet.
I do there probably are some
that are ready for me to move
out of the way so they can move
in to the seat but I am
grateful to be recognized
in front of you all in this
steam chamber and I just want
to thank all of you.
There's several of you have
been out to events at
clubhouses recently including
board PRESIDENT Abandonment
supervisor field supervisor
chan supervisor walton.
We've had these clubhouse youth
the year events and then we are
main youth of the year event
downtown PRESIDENT And thank
you for coming to that.
The mayor came to that as well
as well as supervisor jen so we
love it when supervisors come
out our families love
interacting with you all at the
clubs and seeing the support
that that leaders like you all
extend to the community.
You know, I think a lot about
the the type of services I deal
with boys and girls clubs
across the country and there
aren't many cities that invest
in young people the way this
city does.
So kudos to all of you and your
predecessors who sat in these
seats for the work you do to
empower dcf to do the work it
does the collaboration.
It's really been through a lot
of mayors in those 25 years.
But but as much as you know,
there MAY be you know, back and
forth bickering on this or that
between between the mayor's
office in this chamber it's not
about kids and I feel like
there's pretty good alignment
around the fact that like there
should be a city in which we we
have great services for young
people and opportunities for
for kids to realize their full
potential and that of course
aligns very closely with, you
know, what we're after so thank
you for your investment
in young people.
Thank you for that.
How that investment shows up so
that boys and girls club can do
the work that it does.
Supervisor dorsey, thank you
for calling our attention to
the willie mays clubhouse.
Supervisor walton's been up
there many, many times.
That is a project that I too am
very proud of for now.
We've been there now since 2000
late 2005 the building was
finished renovated in about
2008 and and really has had a
strong impact on that
community.
And then this year we opened up
a new club in sunnydale.
Supervisor walton, thank you
for all your support and making
that club happen.
The transformation of sunnydale
community, the housing
in particular for people there
is truly impactful but our
partnership with mercy housing
and and with wu yi out there
and the opportunity to provide
services so that it's not just
housing but it's services that
can help young people learn,
grow and succeed is is so
important.
>> I'll switch to some some
remarks that I wrote down here.
I'll say that running boys and
girls clubs of san francisco
in this city has really been
one of the blessings of my
life.
>> the work has never been easy
but I've loved every day of it.
>> I feel lucky and proud to
have served this storied
organization which I'll talk a
little bit more about in a
second.
>> I feel lucky to be able to
open doors and build bridges
and expand horizons and
exponentially grow kids
confidence in the skills that
they have.
Speaking of which, I should
introduce this little girl
right here.
This is my youngest daughter
amelia who would probably
rather be any place in the
world but in front of you all.
So if you want to go back to
mom, feel free to all right,
stick with me.
>> I'm I feel lucky to be part
of moments where families are
kind of bursting with pride
when they see their kids
achieve things that they
perhaps didn't think were
attainable.
And I feel lucky to work with
an outstanding group of staff
members who are smart and
talented and hardworking and
passionate about making the
world we live in a better place
.
>> while most people know boys
and girls clubs of san
francisco, not enough people
truly understand the depth and
breadth of our services boys
and girls clubs is a rock solid
organization with a
passionately held set of core
beliefs that keep the bow of
the ship pointed in the right
direction no matter how much
the political social or
economic winds might blow.
The organization was founded
in 1891 south of market street.
We hold the unique distinction
of being two of the original 53
clubs in the country.
We're actually older than boys
and girls clubs of america.
Our mission clubhouse and
supervisor fielder's district
is the first boys and girls
club built west in the
mississippi river back in 1928
was rebuilt in 2010.
This organization is stood
shoulder to shoulder through
all sorts of things two world
wars and you know, two global
pandemics great depression, the
great recession just one thing
after another SEPTEMBER 11th
this organization has stood
with kids through that time.
This club this organization is
one of the very first to serve
kids across the country, one of
the very first to open a club
in public housing, one of the
first to have a computer center
back in the early 1990s we
reached 14,600 kids a year and
as you heard we serve we have
13 different locations across
the city and we have a summer
camp up in mendocino county.
>> so while I appreciate the
personal recognition of my
contribution to the city, this
has always been a team sport
the smartest and the best thing
that I have ever done is to get
and keep talented people around
me.
>> staff like maxine wilson,
lisa rossetti, harold love,
heidi colfer, joanie lockman,
aaron gutierrez and colton
eichelberger have all worked
alongside me for more than 12
years and I have been fortunate
to work with a talented and
generous board and trustees and
I'm honored today.
Ready attention has been called
to some of them to be joined by
my friends greg sir dennis
herrera, derek brown and david
know yola who all have been
tremendously helpful the boys
and girls club and have served
this city with distinction.
>> and I'm also honored to have
my friends rocky freed and
fernando aguilar and sanjay
banker who all serve on our
board here with us today.
>> finally, I'd like to thank
my wife and her two daughters,
one here for all their love and
support.
As you all know from your own
roles, this is a demanding job
and they sacrifice so I can do
this work again.
I want to thank you all for the
honor.
I particularly want to thank
you PRESIDENT Amanda lemon for
calling attention to my service
.
I truly appreciate the
recognition and I look forward
to working with you all to
continue to advance
opportunities for young people
in this city.
>> thank you.
I can do this great.
All right, colleagues, let's go
to roll call first member up to
introduce new business
businesses.
>> you MR. PRESIDENT my
goodness.
>> all right.
I have an ordinance and two
in memoriam first today
supervisor walton and I are
introducing an ordinance to
amend the healthy airport
ordinance which was passed by
this board in NOVEMBER of 2020.
Since the healthy airport
ordinance passed, thousands of
san francisco's airport service
employees have gained or
improved their ability to
provide for the health care
needs of their families.
>> these improved benefits have
helped attract and retain high
quality employees whose work
impacts safety and security
improved airport safety and
security for travelers in the
public by promoting a healthier
workforce and minimize the
potential for contagion to
spread from the airport which
is a major worldwide
transportation hub to other
environs.
The purpose of the amendment
we're introducing today is to
preserve the improvements made
to airport safety and security
through the healthy airport
ordinance while providing
covered employers expanded
flexibility to determine how
best to provide health care
expenditures to their
employees.
I want to thank seiu, U.S. Ww
local two and teamsters local
856 for their feedback on the
legislation.
I want to thank city attorney
in the last off for his work to
draft the legislation I want to
thank supervisor walton for his
ongoing partnership in getting
high quality health care to our
airport service workers and I
want to thank on hire in my
office and natalie g and
supervisor walton's office for
their work on these and on this
amendment.
First in memoriam I have is for
david hagan who died in a car
crash on FEBRUARY 9th at the
age of 72.
Dave was born in san francisco
in 1952.
One of four children he
attended the st theresa's
school archbishop reardon high
school, the university of san
francisco and he earned his mba
mba at golden gate university
where he remained actively
involved in alumni activities.
>> he started his career with a
job at chevron usa where he
worked in the retail marketing
and training division.
Later he launched his own
business the castro street
chevron which is still
in operation today.
Dave later opened gas stations
in westlake and pacific
heights.
He was active in his community
serving on the small business
commission and actively
participating in the san
francisco chamber of commerce,
the merchants of upper market
and castro and the friars club
.
Castro merchants PRESIDENT
Terry austin bennett remember
david as someone who was
passionate about the community
and quietly did everything he
could to support it.
He was only allowed when he
needed to be notwithstanding
all of his community
involvement, dave made time for
his family and friends.
Some of his favorite activities
were dining out with his wife
lynn coaching his children's
sports teams, traveling the
globe, cheering on the giants
and playing with his
granddaughters.
Rest in peace david sagan MAY
your memory be a blessing.
>> then secondly, I'm asking
that we adjourn our meeting
today in memory of charles
phan, the founder and longtime
owner of the slant door who
passed away unexpectedly on
JANUARY 20th at the age of 62.
>> charles was born into light
vietnam in 1962 at the age of
13 following the fall of saigon
,he and his family came to san
francisco as refugees as he
grew up watching his mom and
aunt cook, his interest in food
and cooking also grew.
He studied architecture and
clothing design at uc berkeley
for three years before opening
a vietnamese restaurant.
Despite never having cooked
professionally prior to that
in 1995 the bay area had
already been established as a
global destination for
california cuisine dishes that
focused on simple preparations
of seasonal ingredients sourced
from local farmers.
>> however, while there was an
abundance of italian and french
inspired restaurants that
popularized this approach,
there were no vietnamese
restaurants that specialized
in farm to table.
Then charles opened the
original slanted door on
valencia street inspired by
restaurants like shape in east
and zuni cafe.
Charles created iconic dishes
like his cellophane noodles and
dungeness crab grapefruit and
hikma salad and fish and sauce
.
Carmel claypot chicken made
boneless chicken made with
boneless skin skinless cuts to
accommodate a western audience.
The combination of the slanted
doors bay area farm to table
approach with traditional
vietnamese comfort food and its
upscale westernized style the
service was an immediate hit.
In 2004 slanted door moved to
its grand waterfront location
at the ferry building.
It quickly became one of the
most celebrated restaurants
in all of san francisco and for
a number of years was also the
city's single most lucrative
restaurant.
Both charles and the slanted
door one james beard foundation
awards and charles published
two cookbooks vietnamese home
cooking and the slanted door.
Which one international
association of culinary
professionals awards.
During the pandemic the ferry
building location closed down.
However the slanted doors
remaining locations in napa san
ramone and and bone france,
france, france continue to
operate during the pandemic.
Charles also opened a casual
san shop chuck's takeaway
in the mission he had planned
to bring the slanted door back
to valencia street later this
year.
Rest in peace and power charles
fan MAY your memory be a
blessing and the rest I submit
.
>> thank you MR. PRESIDENT.
Supervisor melgar thank you,
MADAM Clerk.
>> colleagues happy women's
history month.
At this month we will be
celebrating the contributions
of women to our city state, our
country, our world
in highlighting and fighting
against all the ways in which
we are still unequal
economically, politically,
socially and now face new
threats under this current
administration.
I look forward to this board
weighing in to make this a
memorable MARCH for women
in our city.
I also wanted to bring to your
attention that this morning the
supreme court of the united
states handed down a decision
in favor of san francisco
in the san francisco versus epa
lawsuit that was the subject of
a resolution I authored last
year and we passed the decision
as folks in the environmental
movement feared was not narrow.
>> today's supreme court ruling
has confirmed what we feared
this was a misguided effort
that has resulted in a pyrrhic
victory.
So while the city and county of
san francisco prevailed, the
decision will have an enduring
and damaging loss for the
environmental protection
agency, the clean water act and
the american people.
>> it is deeply troubling to me
to see san francisco, a city
known for its environmental
leadership, play a significant
role in weakening the very
protections that safeguard our
water and natural resources not
just for us but for the entire
country.
This decision aligns with
PRESIDENT Trump's broader
rollback of environmental
regulations and I fear the long
term consequences for the
environment in the united
states and it will be severe.
So despite today's ruling, the
san francisco public utilities
commission still has a
responsibility to uphold the
highest standards for water
quality and environmental
stewardship.
Combined sewer overflows
continue to discharge millions
of gallons of wastewater
untreated into the bay and
pacific ocean every time we
have rains and we're having
more of them more often because
the climate crisis is real.
We must do better regardless of
this decision our commitment to
protecting the environment
in san francisco and in our
country must remain steadfast.
And the rest I submit.
Thank you.
Supervisor sartor submit thank
you.
Supervisor sherril collins.
>> today I'm introducing three
pieces of legislation.
First I'm introducing
legislation to create an
entertainment zone on union
street.
I am extremely excited about
the possibility not only of
just allowing businesses to
have a little bit more
flexibility to serve their
customers, to serve their
community and just frankly have
more fun but also to increase
the vibrancy of both district
two and san francisco
throughout this city our
restaurants, bars and small
businesses are still fighting
to recover.
And I think it's incredibly
important to note that 2024 was
perhaps the hardest year for
restaurants since 2008.
And we need to be doing more to
help them thrive.
Entertainment zones work.
We've seen them introduced
recently by PRESIDENT Mandell
and we've seen them transform
places like front street and
thrive city and now it is union
street's turn.
>> this legislation builds on
the success of our union street
festival an annual event that
brings thousands of visitors to
district two and now by
establish an entertainment zone
during the festival.
We want to encourage these
visitors to eat and drink at
our many lovely brick and
mortar restaurants on union
street which is going to
massively support these shops
bottom lines.
>> now I've spoken to business
owners who are ready and eager
for this for this zone and I'm
grateful to have the support of
these shops and the support of
regan company, the head of the
union street merchants
association who's been a great
advocate for the health of this
corridor and frankly more
energy on the streets benefits
everyone.
These activations make our
shops a destination and
encourages more opportunities
to inject energy, energy,
energy into our merchant areas
by expanding the number of
entertainment zones.
And I'm looking forward to
being back talking on this same
topic again soon.
San francisco continues to lead
the way in supporting our small
businesses.
This is a simple step.
It's a simple step but it's an
effective step towards making
our commercial corridors
stronger, more vibrant and
built to last.
We simply need to make it
easier for to succeed in san
francisco especially for our
small businesses.
And I look forward to working
with all of you to make this a
reality and to continue to
finding ways to bring life
energy and vibrancy back to our
neighborhoods.
Next I'm calling for a hearing
to examine how the department
of homelessness, the support of
housing is structuring and
managing its contracts.
Now this is not just a
bureaucratic exercise.
This is about accountability.
This is about transparency.
And this is about ensuring that
taxpayer dollars are driving
real results.
Right now hca has roughly 300
contract contracts in place but
we don't have a clear picture
of how many of these contract
include specific performance
metrics, specific
accountability measures and
what the outcomes that those
contracts are intended to do
drive towards.
>> we need to understand
whether we are holding
contractors accountable for
delivering those outcomes,
whether those outcomes are the
ones we want, whether these
outcomes are even set up for
success with realistic funding
and whether we're issuing
contracts competitively or
defaulting to sole source
agreements that limit oversight
and efficiency.
We need to invest in programs
that are actually moving the
needle because quite frankly
homelessness as we all know is
one of the most pervasive
issues in san francisco.
Every district, every san
franciscan, whether it's
individuals who are
experiencing homelessness or
otherwise are impacted by this
crisis.
Not to say our perceptions of
safety or economic recovery and
the overall health of this
city.
If we're serious about solving
this crisis and I think we as a
group are very serious about
solving this crisis, we have to
be just as serious about how we
manage and evaluate the
services we're paying for.
I want to thank the mayor's
office.
I want to thank and the
comptroller's office and the
city administrator for being
willing to join this hearing to
answer key questions about the
contracting process and
performance tracking.
The goal is not just to
identify issues.
Frankly, we already know that
many of these contracts are
being scrutinized.
We want this goal of this
hearing to be to work together
to establish a new and
consistent contracting standard
moving forward to deliver real
results for san franciscans.
This hearing needs to be about
not having gotchas for the
public servants who work so
hard for us and for all san
francisco.
This needs to be about starting
a conversation and driving
towards a shared success not
only on the board of
supervisors but with sage as
well.
I also want to credit my
predecessor assembly member
katherine stefani who has long
championed this kind of fiscal
oversight with a focus on
efficiency.
Without her leadership we MAY
not be in the position to hold
this hearing.
And I'm grateful for her
continued focus on these
critical critical issues.
Simply put, we need a
contracting process that
matches the urgency of the
crisis we're facing.
>> and this hearing is a step
toward that standard.
Finally, I'm introducing a
resolution in support of the
assembly bill five 458 excuse
me introduced by assembly
member katherine stefani.
She and I share deep focus on
safety regarding gun violence
and preventing gun violence our
communities.
This this measure will bring
much needed transparency and
safety to california's firearm
procurement process.
A recent investigation by brady
united against gun violence
revealed that california law
enforcement agencies lack a
rigorous vetting process when
choosing firearm vendors.
this means that public funds
are being funneled to
businesses with documented
history of violence violating
federal firearm regulations.
I want to give assembly member
stefani an enormous amount of
credit for being create time
and time again for pushing the
boundaries on preventing gun
violence and ensuring that
firearm related safety is not
just the standard but a
priority for all of us.
If a firearm dealer
manufacturer fails to meet
these compliance standards or
refuses to disclose their
history of federal trace
requests, inspection records or
compliance appliance
violations, their contracts
will be canceled.
Their bids will be rejected.
Thank you to assembly member
stefani for your leadership.
This is beyond just sensible
gun policy.
This is about keeping our
families safe.
And I am incredibly grateful to
you.
>> the rest I submit.
Thank you supervisor sheryl
supervisor walton thank you so
much, MADAM Clerk and
colleagues.
>> today I will be introducing
a resolution urging the mayor's
office and the department of
homelessness and support of
housing to explore locations
for unhoused shelters
throughout san francisco.
San francisco has been in a
homeless crisis and while the
city has expanded shelters and
supportive housing, the reality
is some districts are carrying
way more of the weight than
others right now.
Districts ten, nine, six and
five have the majority of
shelters and services while
other neighborhoods especially
in the western parts of the
city have very few or none at
all.
>> this isn't equitable
especially considering the
concentration of our unhoused
neighbors in other areas of san
francisco the same communities
many of which are lower income
and home to people of color
keep getting asked to do more.
While other areas haven't
stepped up in the same way
homelessness is a citywide
issue and like my colleagues
supervisors sherril just shared
a few moments ago a san
francisco issue and every
district should be part of the
solution not just a handful and
not just the east side of the
city.
>> our office has been working
with hhs each the last year to
implement a 2.25 acre
industrial site on girard
avenue to build a village of 68
tiny homes with 20 rv parking
sites.
But our office was informed by
the mayor's team that instead
of the proposed plans vetted by
and discussed with community
they now want to do a bait and
switch and build a homeless
shelter with 200 plus homeless
beds and eliminate the safe
parking.
>> this site was supposed to be
hybrid a mixture of folks
living in tiny homes and
in vehicles and with a much
smaller footprint.
We also have four other
homeless shelters in district
ten including 128 bed
navigation center on bayshore
boulevard.
>> if you could show me the
data and the plans for homeless
shelters throughout the city as
promised then we will be having
an equitable conversation.
This resolution is about making
sure we distribute shelters and
provide services for our
unhoused neighbors more
equitably across san francisco
.
It's not about forcing
something on neighborhoods.
It's about asking every
district to do its part.
We need to have an open
community driven process where
new shelters sites are placed
in a way that makes sense and
serves people effectively.
If we're serious about
addressing homelessness, we
have to stop overburdening the
same neighborhoods and make
sure resources are shared
across the entire city.
This is about fairness, equity
and making real progress on one
of the biggest challenges we
face here in san francisco.
I also just want to briefly
state that I'm continuing to
co-sponsor the healthy airport
ordinance with PRESIDENT
Malaman.
I want to thank our labor
partners who have been in this
process with us to make these
changes.
And I also want to thank
PRESIDENT Randleman for
acknowledging our staff for
their hard work on this and the
rest.
I submit.
>> thank you.
Supervisor walton supervisor
chan submit.
Thank you.
Supervisor chin.
Submit.
>> thank you.
Supervisor dorsey thank you,
MADAM Clerk.
Colleagues in preparation for
legislation I am working on
with board PRESIDENT Rafael
millman.
I'm today submitting a letter
of inquiry on the resources
necessary to implement a
wastewater drug testing program
for the city and county of san
francisco.
We're seeking responses from
three city agencies our
department of public health,
public utilities commission and
office of the chief medical
examiner to offer us one an
estimation of resources and
staffing necessary to implement
such a wastewater based
epidemiology or wbe program.
Two additional policy or
resource considerations we
should be aware of as we
legislate this program into
existence.
>> and three any available
results from san francisco's
participation in a bio bot
analytics pilot that the
national institute on drug
abuse started as the wastewater
surveillance program in 2023
and 2024.
This kind of program would
enable us to measure progress
in our fentanyl and
methamphetamine crisis and also
to monitor for deadly new drugs
and drug adulterants like tranq
measurement metal modine and
others.
Although relatively new
in north america, wastewater
drug testing has been used
successfully in europe for the
last 15 years and I look
forward to the forthcoming
information and partnership
from the relevant departments
and colleagues in this effort.
And before submitting I would
ask that I be referred after
supervisor maclean's
introduction.
>> thank you.
Supervisor dorsey supervisor
and gaudio submit.
Thank you.
Supervisor mahmood.
>> colleagues today I would
like to introduce legislation
to help bring our into the
21st century.
>> I firmly believe that city
hall should work for the people
and that is elected officials.
It is our duty to do all we can
to make our run smarter, to
better serve the public.
>> that's why I'm introducing
legislation today to tackle
archaic bureaucracy preventing
key city departments from
accessing data and information
subscriptions that would
benefit their work.
>> with the support from the
city attorney city
administrator, assessor
recorder, treasurer and city
librarian, the data and
information subscriptions
legislation peels back
unnecessary approval layers and
lengthy procedures that have
delayed city departments from
securing the essential digital
subscriptions needed to ensure
city operations run smoothly.
>> this legislation provides
simple software access for city
departments and empowers them
to save time, access more
vendors and ultimately serve
san franciscans better.
>> if we look at the current
code this legislation is
amending we see it was written
in the 1990s when physical book
manuals were in vogue.
As a result certain departments
like the treasurer and assessor
recorder are delayed for months
every year in purchasing the
software they need while others
like the city librarian have to
provide outdated paper manuals
instead of digital content
subscriptions to residents who
rely on their public resources.
>> the current contracting
bureaucracy is so cumbersome
for vendors that some tech
companies won't even bother
selling their product to the
city.
Putting our at a very serious
disadvantage it doesn't have to
be this way and this
legislation is simply table
stakes.
If we want to bring our city
into the 21st century and this
is just the beginning with this
new administration city hall
and a collective will for
collaboration legislation such
as this demonstrates the public
that we are making strides to
improve efficiency, modernize
archaic code and foster
collaborative forward thinking
solutions.
>> I'd like to thank my
colleagues board PRESIDENT
Mendelsohn and supervisors
melgar sadr and sheryl for
co-sponsoring this legislation.
I'd also like to thank our
department head city attorney
david chu, city administrator
carmen chu, city librarian
michael lambert, treasurer jose
cisneros and assessor recorder
joaquin torres for their
steadfast support of this
ordinance and for collaborating
with my office to address this
issue.
I'm deeply thankful to the
public servants in our city
hall colleagues in this city
administrator's office, city
library assessor recorder and
treasurer's offices who
provided exemplary service to
residents and came together to
help bring the solution forward
to our office.
>> specifically sophia hayward
simon j.
>> jackson.
Holly lung.
Molly peterson.
Joe spice teasel shaw.
Eric manky.
Angela yip.
>> mike fernandez marcus lynge
alex barrett shorter and amanda
freed.
And a special thank you to sam
logan and my chief jessica
gutierrez garcia in our office
for their hard work on this
ordinance.
Second, I'd like to today
introduce a resolution that is
deeply personal to me as the
first muslim elected to the
board of supervisors.
It is my absolute honor to
introduce a resolution honoring
the commencement of ramadan and
recognizing the contributions
of san francisco's muslim
community.
>> the san francisco bay area
hosts one of the largest and
most diverse muslim populations
in the nation with over 250,000
residents from various ethnic
and cultural backgrounds.
>> in my own neighborhood the
tenderloin has been long been a
hub for immigrant communities
including many muslim families
,small businesses and faith
based organizations that
provide critical services such
as food distribution, housing
support and workforce
development to underserved
residents.
>> it's a home for a
significant population of
muslim and swanson children who
deserve meaningful investment,
supportive resources and safe
spaces for growth, education
and well-being as well as a
broader sense of security that
allows all residents to thrive
without fear or harm.
>> in recent years there's been
a wider acceptance and
awareness of muslim holidays.
For example, in AUGUST 2022 the
san francisco board of
education passed a resolution
recognizing eidl fitr and as
district holidays.
And this is important because
muslim students in california
experienced bullying at twice
the national rate underscoring
the urgent need for inclusive
policies and protections within
our schools.
>> the islamic center of san
francisco has evolved into a
multifaceted community hub
addressing religious,
educational and social needs
and local muslim owned
businesses including halal
grocers, restaurants and
service providers contribute to
the culture and economic
vitality of san francisco.
>> and many of them offering
free iftar meals when we break
our fasts every day for the
next 30 days to those in need
during this holy month.
>> it's important to recognize
and name the policies that
target unfortunately during
this national times muslim
individuals and families which
is having a lasting impact on
those who live in our city and
at this time reaffirm san
francisco's stance against
islamophobia and all forms of
religious discrimination.
>> there's been a rise in these
concerns regarding immigration
and this resolution seeks to
reaffirm san francisco's
commitment to supporting these
immigrant communities
especially the immigrants and
refugees during this holy month
of ramadan.
>> ramadan is the ninth month
of the islamic lunar calendar.
It's a sacred time for fasting
reflection, spiritual renewal
and communal solidarity.
The observance of ramadan 2025
commenced last friday, FEBRUARY
28th and will continue until
the evening of saturday MARCH
29th during which time muslims
will fast from dawn to sunset
engage in prayer and
participate in charity.
>> this resolution commands the
contributions of local muslim
led organizations and community
groups and reaffirms the city's
unwavering commitment to being
a safe and inclusive space for
all muslims and all
marginalized groups in this
district and in the city.
>> it recognizes their
essential role and our
essential role to immigrants
and refugees in shaping our
history.
It acknowledges the increased
investment that we should be
doing for the well-being and
education safety of the muslim
and swanson children in the
tenderloin.
And it welcomes all san
franciscans to join in this
honoring this holy and blessed
month of ramadan.
And I'll close on this note by
mentioning to my colleagues if
I look hangry or tired over the
next month it's not personal.
>> I just haven't eaten since
sunup.
So lastly I'd like to introduce
an in memoriam.
>> and colleagues I'd ask that
we adjourn today in today's
meeting in memory of mark ezra
who passed away in JANUARY
after a life of musical
storytelling and devoted
passion for the japantown
community.
>> his wife is his wife.
Brenda is in the audience.
She will need to stand while we
read the in memoriam.
>> mark was born across the bay
in vallejo in 1954 and attended
san francisco state university.
He worked as a van driver for
japantown senior organization
committee while becoming
immersed in the fillmore music
scene of the 19 70s.
>> mark would go on to be a
pioneer in the asian-american
jazz movement combining the
spiritual and improvizational
elements of jazz with east
asian instrumentation.
In addition to the upright
bass, he became a master of the
show a mouth organ more
commonly found in japanese
traditional music that sounds
right at home on mark's jazz
contributions.
>> he toured internationally
and frequently collaborated
with his wife brenda wong aoki
on multi-media pieces that
weaved together music dance
theater and spoken word
storytelling to share the
asian-american experience with
generations including the
history of japanese internment
in san francisco and the
redevelopment of the western
tradition.
>> while his musical influence
can be felt across the world,
he was a thorough through and
through san franciscan.
>> his love for the city
inspired his music and he was
proud to hail from georgetown
and the fillmore.
He served as director of the
san francisco asian american
jazz festival helping cement
the city's place at the heart
of the genre.
He was also generous with his
time to the japantown community
serving as a founding member of
and contributing artists to the
japantown cultural district and
teaching third graders at rosa
parks elementary school.
>> I first met mark and brenda
at the cherry blossom festival
parade last year.
They MARCH every year with the
japanese american religious
federation or giraffe.
>> a coalition of christian,
buddhist and shinto spiritual
leaders j r f began in the
japanese prison camps because
in realizing the challenging
nature of the times spiritual
leaders concluded it was better
to all work together.
>> the darkness of those times
was reflected meaningfully
in mark's music as its theme is
recognize not only the deep
history and trauma of the time
but celebrates and honors the
enduring resiliency and
triumphant spirit of the
japanese-american community.
Mark is survived by his wife
and frequent artistic and life
collaborator brenda.
Their son K.K. And
granddaughter lucy and his two
brothers.
>> rest in peace marcie xue.
MAY your memory be a blessing.
>> thank you.
Thank you.
Supervisor mahmood.
Supervisor dorsey you asked to
be referred?
>> yes.
Thank you, MADAM Clerk.
And thanks especially to my
pioneering colleague supervisor
mahmood.
It is an honor to add my voice
in support of his resolution
declaring the commencement of
ramadan here in the city and
county of san francisco.
Ramadan is a sacred time
observed by millions around the
world and right here at home a
month centered on prayer,
reflection and fasting but also
on deep community recognition,
generosity and compassion.
In san francisco we are
privileged to be home to a
vibrant and diverse muslim
community that contributes so
much to the fabric of our city.
Whether it's through small
business ownership, civic
engagement, public service or
simply being good neighbors,
our muslim community enriches
san francisco in immeasurable
ways as we mark the beginning
of this holy month.
Let us also reflect on the ways
all of us as a city can embody
the spirit of ramadan by
extending grace, mercy and
understanding to those most
in need.
Whether it's through feeding
the hungry, caring for our
unhoused neighbors or simply
showing kindness in our daily
interactions.
The lessons of ramadan are a
call to action for all of us
regardless of our faith.
In a city that prides itself on
inclusivity and compassion,
ramadan offers us a welcome
opportunity to recommit to
those values and to affirm the
dignity of all san franciscans.
Although my personal stake
in this resolution is not as a
member of the muslim faith
myself, I am blessed to have on
my team the board of the board
of supervisors only muslim
legislative aide johannes ebadi
who is a standout community
leader in multiple respects
including elevating recognition
for and celebrating ramadan
across our city.
When we honor the traditions of
our neighbors, we strengthen
the very foundation of who we
are as san franciscans a place
where everyone belongs and
where every faith and culture
is embraced and uplifted.
Ramadan kareem to all who
observed and now the rest I
submit.
>> thank you supervisor dorsey.
MR. PRESIDENT, seeing no more
names on the roster that
concludes the introduction of
new business.
>> all right, let's go to
public comment.
At this time the board welcomes
the general public comment of
members of the in the audience.
please line up to your right
hand side of the chamber
alongside the curtains.
You MAY speak to the approval
of the meeting minutes as
presented.
Other general matters that are
not on today's agenda but are
within the board subject matter
jurisdiction.
All other agenda content has
been reported out to the board
by an appropriate committee
where the public comment
requirement was satisfied.
>> let's hear from our first
speaker.
We're setting the timer for two
minutes.
>> welcome.
>> hi obsidian.
Even if these unfortunately
included the genocide, this
nation was created by
christians with a protestant or
catholics this tradition must
remain for balance.
>> before I forget the black
history month is racism
in disguise.
>> like any community you want
to celebrate because you create
divisions which we don't want.
>> sorry.
You understand?
We won't have it.
>> no specific z y x w v utc
occupy and mlk g I g w use it.
>> hey b c d.
>> okay so you get the alphabet
reverse very league c google
reverse alphabet you see?
>> stop messing with the guys I
told you.
Yeah.
You need to address the problem
of laser manipulation.
Weather manipulation not only
include the poisoning of food.
You need to address this before
i declare officially that you
are part of the which is fake
and that wants to kill the
people.
>> so there is nothing to
celebrate at all except the
revolution which is going to
prison.
Yes, but to taking care of our
fellow creatures every living
species.
>> okay.
Meanwhile no qr codes.
You need to get rid of your
cell phones.
>> no qr codes boycott totally
.
No digital I.D..
Coming.
Sorry.
If you insist.
>> there would be no idea at
all.
>> okay.
13 seconds.
What did I forget?
>> people don't want the great
highway to be closed.
Yeah.
>> no, we don't want it.
We want to have it.
>> there is more.
Okay.
Are you.
>> thank you for your comments.
Welcome to the next speaker.
>> hello.
My name is liam mckeever.
I live in d6 and I am convinced
I am a political target of my
supervisor matt dorsey.
I wrote this poem on MARCH 1st,
2025 for the board.
War warfare there is no fair
war.
Did I ever imagine imagine I'd
be a target for war?
My deploys men to attack me
psychologically bordering on
physical.
when will that border be
ignored?
Did I ever imagine latinas
would go along with it?
Ones too.
What an unco aided bitter pill
to swallow.
>> did I ever imagine as a
child who grew up on military
bases whose father was deployed
to war that I'd be in one with
you?
No.
No I did not.
Am I paying for that sin of my
american father?
How can this war be fair
against a nobody like me,
against the souls I fight for
abused souls who have nothing
but cold liberal smiles
pledging support as they deploy
more men to terrorize us on the
streets.
No war is fair.
Indeed I appreciate that no one
looked at me during that.
You all looked at your screens
instead.
You prefer me in two
dimensional instead of me and
three dimensional.
You don't want me to be a
human.
I don't know what you want me
to be but I'm not that.
>> I'm not a two dimensional
object.
I was raised catholic.
>> I'm not anymore.
I'm an atheist.
I have a lot of problems with
the church but I never had a
problem with the teachings of
jesus christ.
Love thy neighbor.
That is all I am guilty of is
loving my neighbors.
And I don't know why you allow
me to be punished for it by
your colleagues.
I wish you did feel shame.
>> thank you for your comments.
Welcome.
>> good afternoon.
Board of supervisors.
For the record, my name is
chris ward klein.
Yesterday I spoke at the health
commission and I've been here
about 20 plus times and I'm
starting to realize why I
shouldn't be because there's a
watchdog within the san
francisco and it's the city
attorney and dennis herrera and
everything that I brought up
should have been brought up to
each of you every single time.
But it hasn't.
And my main concern is to 50
kearny street and this was
reported to the mayor and other
key leaders within the last 12
months there have been over 12
deaths of veterans, multiple
arsons, violent incidents and
staff members who have been
targeted as well with injuries,
health issues and other issues
that were caused by one system
gang surveillance, health
surveillance call it whatever
you want.
These veterans have already
been at war living at 250
kearny street is like living
through vietnam.
The gulf war or iraq all over
again.
The bigger issue here is that
after during or after all
pandemics people use health
surveillance, gang
surveillance, whatever you want
to call it and the manner to
attempt to write their own
ticket and always ends with a
scandal.
For example, during the 1918
pandemic led to the black sox
scandal and baseball the ccny
point shaving scandal in 1951,
the dixie classic scandals
in 1961 boston college point
shaving scandal right after the
swine flu of 1976 and the
russian flu of 1977 and the
tulane men's basketball point
shaving scandal in 1984 all
during or after a pandemic.
And if you're not aware there
is a massive point shaving
investigation happening right
now by the fbi reported by
sports illustrated and it's
going to topple all of those
combined.
It is a massive investigation.
This is why the nfl has
mandatory protocols for
injuries and concussions.
They force players to sit out
for certain number of weeks as
they know of health
surveillance and the illegal
advantage it could give your
team, for example.
Magic johnson was not allowed
to play not because of hiv but
because he would have been on
health surveillance by L.A. And
that would have given him a
potential advantage over other
players not that he needed it.
Thank you.
>> thank you for your comments.
Welcome to the next speaker.
>> good reading.
Board of supervisors.
My name is richard sd peterson
.
>> I am 82 years old and I've
been waiting and waiting
waiting.
Seven and a half years ago I
applied to build a house on
three lots in lower valley.
Yes.
First I had to combine the lots
and divide the lots and that
process was taking all of this
time I need to get this
entitled before I die.
In fact I had to put my my
property in a revokable trust
just because people thought
that I wouldn't make it before
the house was built.
>> so why is it taking so long?
Well, I know why it takes long.
This I have in my hand is a
1099 form from the federal
that all small employers must
fill out.
>> you can't replace it and
that starts a long journey.
>> well surely they must you
can type into this and and it
comes out on the page.
No you need carbon papers.
Where do you get carbon papers?
Where do you get a typewriter
and impact typewriter?
The big companies all have
impact machines that they can
comply with but the little guy
is left in a compliance
nightmare and that I'm afraid
is what's happening with this
city and trying to comply with
the planning department and the
building department.
>> it's sad but I hope I get my
dream house built one that I
can't afford to live in or
afford to maintain.
But I would like to see it
built.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Like speaker.
>> my name is jim mcafee and
I'm the domestic partner of a
victim at laguna honda hospital
and rehabilitation.
And several times I have given
testimony to the board of
supervisors and the health
commission that does not report
the share of cost from patients
at laguna honda hospital.
>> what they do report on is
patient services revenue.
>> they never report on patient
share of cost revenue.
It is fraudulent to not include
all revenue that laguna honda
gets.
I have the documents right here
and it's by drew moral the
chief financial officer to the
health commission.
>> can you guys make a copy of
this for the board of
supervisors?
>> thank you for your comments
.
>> welcome to the next speaker
>> good afternoon.
PRESIDENT Of the board
supervisors I'd like to speak
on item 37.
Good afternoon.
My name is nick colina.
I'm the cfo of ankle iron and
construction and one of the
founding members of the sfl
bba and build out california.
I wanted to take this time to
personally thank supervisor
walton, supervisor mendham and
supervisor dorsey and
in sponsoring the lbw e
resolution.
>> l b e's are the economic
engine of the city.
We provide union paying jobs
and lobbies hire locally.
>> we spend our dollars with
local suppliers as well.
Storefronts are often supported
in regards to the rebuild of
san francisco but we believe
that local contractors play a
huge part in the in the
revitalized zation of our
beautiful city.
By creating generational wealth
with these union paying jobs.
I wanted to take this time to
talk about the lbe program
during the 2009 recession my
dad drove me around bayview and
showed me how many for sale and
for lease signs that were
posted on many of the
warehouses.
These were rlb eas many of
which are fellow business
owners and friends.
>> after chapter 14 b passed
that changed and turned the
water on just a little bit for
us from the data provided from
cmd.
We found that our collective of
lbb spend over $77 million
in wages in san francisco.
Many of these are good paying
union jobs that go to workers
who live in underrepresented
communities like the mission
excelsior and the bayview.
So when the lv l b program is
referred to at the budget
committee as a social handout
that's offensive and simply not
true.
What we are is the an economic
engine and the economic engine
of the city.
So let's work together to come
up with solutions to strengthen
our lp.
>> thank you for your comments.
Welcome.
MS. Brown eddie in afternoon
I'm here.
You know as usual as I come to
talk about my son arbor albert
castle who was murdered AUGUST
14th and I heard you saying
that the brady campaign and all
the gun buyback acts are
successful.
But if they're a successful,
then why aren't these homicides
being solved?
>> I've been coming to the
police commission every
wednesday and prior to this
here every tuesday.
>> it's been a while back but
we I show all these pictures of
all the unsolved homicides of
the young man, the cases that
aren't being signed.
>> people are walking around
with boys are walking around
with bullets in them.
They're just not dead.
>> okay.
So what do we do as a board of
supervisor?
I'm also asking, you know the
resolution approval for the
resolution urging the board of
supervisors to amend the san
francisco homicide reward
policy.
I'm still waiting for that to
be implemented and I'm praying
that you know, I've talked with
you matt darcy on getting this
done and I'm waiting for this
to happen because it would help
us mothers if you find other
ways to pay tipsters to come
forth about these murders and
homicides and so mothers like
myself and others mothers can
heal somewhat heal.
You know I mean I'm having a
street named after him but you
know, the case is unsolved.
My child still lives and with
wealth he's never going to be
with me again.
>> but I do urge you please to
to prove this.
Approve this resolution and
that MARCH quarter over stone
brought to the board of
supervisors and I'm just
praying this happens.
I will never stop fighting for
my child.
I love him.
he was my only child.
>> and if you have children
please understand what I'm
saying.
Don't let this hit your home
and then you're going to want
to help.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Let's welcome our next speaker
.
>> good afternoon, PRESIDENT
And the board members.
My name is darryl and davis and
I'm a small business owner
in san francisco.
Since 1996 I sit on the j c
advisory committee and have
said so for quite a number of
years and I'm here to support
the resolution of supervisor
walton resolution 37 and I'm
urging you to support this
resolution because for small
businesses and san franciscans
to succeed we need equitable
fair opportunity to bid on
contracts that are in san
francisco.
There is a lot of money that
runs through san francisco
through contracting and it's
oftentimes small businesses who
are get the short end of those
contracts and the lbb program
14 b is the only resource that
ensures that small businesses
get a fair share of equitable
contracting in san francisco.
Go and we urge you to be on the
right side of this issue.
The we are facing incredible
crisis in our country around
equity and inclusion and
participation and we are
depending on you as elected
officials to stand up and
support and continue to support
small businesses in san
francisco.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Welcome to our next speaker.
>> good afternoon supervisors.
PRESIDENT Randleman my name is
tricia gregory.
I'm also a member of the lp
advisory committee and I am a
micro L.B. I own a trucking
company in district ten for the
last 22 years and I'm still a
micro lp so that says a lot.
I do also strongly urge you to
approve supervisor walton's
resolution in affirming the san
francisco lp a's and 14 b you'd
like the supervisor here said
earlier you guys will do
everything to support the
businesses the I mean the
restaurants, the bars but we
need more support with local
contracting.
I also would like to thank
supervisor walton and his
office and PRESIDENT Management
for being champions of the l b
e community.
It does mean a lot to us and we
do appreciate all your hard
work in supporting us.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Let's welcome our next speaker
.
>> good afternoon.
Our board of supervisors and
thank you for your all your
work.
I'm samuel adams, executive of
construction and community
development for baines group
inc.
We're a general contractor
local san francisco contractor.
>> I'm in support of item 37.
I want to give you some facts
of why we're in support of it
and why it's important for the
city or county of san francisco
.
As a san francisco L.B.
Contractor we are able to
provide opportunities for sfb
trade partners and subcontract
commitments.
This entails opportunities for
local workforce that creates
community empowerment.
So for example two of our
affordable housing, housing
construction blocks and
sundials are a combined
approximate $100 million gmp.
And so with those dollars we're
about 30% of contract dollars
going to lbe east 33% going to
local san francisco workforce
and about 8% of priority zip
code san francisco local
workforce the same and a half
point shipyard that's a
combined blocks two blocks
approximately 90 million dp gmp
dollars above 20% of
subcontract dollars going to
lbj is 14% of par a priority
zip codes going to san
francisco local workforce 36%
of local san francisco
workforce.
So these are really good
numbers.
These are dollars going right
back into the community.
>> simple fact as a gec we've
been able to sit at the table a
larger gcs and cut some of
these deals and continued to
filter money down to our local
businesses.
So thank you for listening to
me in support of this item.
>> thank you for your comments
.
>> welcome.
Shalom in hebrew means peace.
>> my name is aliya chandler
and I am a abolitionist and a
social justice fighter for my
people, for my nation and I'm
also a hebrew woman.
My son was murdered on JANUARY
the 9th 2015 the san francisco
quadruple homicide four young
men shot to death in hayes
valley I fall for almost ten
years to get a trial date and I
finally got one on SEPTEMBER
the 18th two weeks later on
SEPTEMBER the 28th I had a
stroke hospitalized for two
weeks.
>> I shoot and I had a stroke
to fight for the injustice of
making sure that the trial went
forward according to the
$250,000 reward that was
assigned to my son case three
requirements to find the person
who committed the crime it must
be a conviction and you must be
a witness.
I was the reason the arrest
took place a year and seven
months later I was supposed to
be a witness on the stand.
The D.A. Took me off two weeks
because they didn't want me to
speak that the trial should not
have went according to count
number seven.
Count number seven was you was
not supposed to try this court
in a rico act.
They decided to do it anyway.
That's why I took three three.
It took ten years.
However, the jury made a
statement and told the judge
after the conviction that they
had to drop kill seven which
now the case is on hold if it's
found out that the appellate
court three judges allowed this
court this trial to go forward,
it's going to be an
investigation.
MARCH 10th is supposed to be
the sentencing FEBRUARY that
was supposed to be the
sentencing because MR. Lee
finally realized that he should
not have had to trial in the
name of the rico act number
seven account number seven.
I'm trying to just rush our
request in for the 250 thousand
because I'm the reasonable for
arrest took place.
>> I would thank you, MS..
Chandler are there any other
members of the public who would
like to address the board
during general public comment?
MR. PRESIDENT all right.
>> seeing no other speakers
public comment is now closed
and I believe we have been
joined by supervisor fielder
who I believe would like to be
referred for roll call.
>> thank you so much.
PRESIDENT Randleman good
afternoon colleagues, city
staff and members of the
public.
Today I'm announcing a hearing
focused on a comprehensive and
proven approach to our city's
drug crisis.
>> the four pillars strategy
san franciscans deserve real
solutions.
We know that the status quo is
not working.
The mission like many parts of
the city, is experiencing the
highly visible impacts of
public drug use and these
impacts are not just about what
we see.
>> they're about the lives lost
to overdose the families
grieving and the communities
trying to hold it all together.
Since taking office I've met
with small business owners,
community based organizations
and countless neighbors
neighbors from across district
nine.
>> their message has been clear
they want to see an end to
fatal drug overdoses.
They want an end to open air
drug scenes.
And they want to feel safe and
supported in their own
neighborhoods.
>> the four pillars strategy
offers us a path forward.
It's model is with a proven
track record based on four key
areas prevention, treatment,
harm reduction and enforcement
.
>> and it's proven to work not
just in theory but in practice.
>> in the 1990s zurich,
switzerland faced a crisis very
similar to ours.
>> deplorable street conditions
is soaring addiction rates and
an overdose epidemic.
>> but after implementing the
four pillars strategy, zurich
transformed into one of the
safest cities in the world.
>> and here's the most
important part according to our
own budget and legislative
analysts, it is transferrable
to san francisco's fentanyl
crisis.
>> but to make it work we have
to go all in.
Up until now we've only
deployed parts of this strategy
and we've done so unevenly.
The result has been temporary
improvements in some areas of
the city while other
neighborhoods like the mission
feel the displacement of drug
markets and the same cycle of
harm.
>> one of the key lessons from
zurich is the deep
collaboration between law
enforcement public health
officials and social service
professionals working together
side by side day in and day
out.
>> this is not about choosing
between public safety and
public health.
It's about bringing them
together.
>> we cannot continue to push
the problem from one part of
the city to another.
We cannot keep relying on 1 or
2 strategies when we know that
it takes all four working
together.
And so at this upcoming hearing
that I'm calling for, we will
hear directly from our city
departments that contributed to
the four pillars report
commissioned by this board and
published by the bill last
NOVEMBER.
>> we will learn about what it
would take to implement the
strategies citywide and how we
can build the infrastructure to
make it last through ongoing
inter-agency collaboration and
regular oversight.
>> we have an opportunity right
now to move beyond piecemeal
solutions and take bold
comprehensive action.
>> the four pillars strategy
gives us the roadmap.
And now it's up to us to follow
it.
>> I want to thank supervisor
dorsey for being eager and
willing to co-sponsor this
hearing.
I look forward to working with
him with the mayor.
>> my colleagues on the board,
our city departments and most
importantly our communities to
deliver lasting solutions to
this crisis.
>> thank you.
>> I submit thank you.
Supervisor fielder.
With that MADAME Clerk let's go
to our for adoption of that
committee reference agenda
items 37 through 40 items 30
seven through 40 were
introduced for adoption but
without committee reference.
A unanimous vote is required
for adoption of a resolution on
first reading today.
Alternatively, a member MAY
require a resolution on first
reading to go to committee.
>> supervisor what?
Thank you please for item 37.
Okay.
Anybody else?
All right.
On the remaining balance of the
items MADAM Clerk, can you
please call the roll on items
38 through 40.
>> supervisor randleman hi
randleman I'm supervisor melgar
melgar I supervisor sutter
sutter I supervisor sherril
sherril I supervisor walton hi
walton I'm supervisor chin chin
eyes supervisor chin chin eyes
supervisor dorsey dorsey I
supervisor engardio and
engardio I supervisor fielder
fielder I and supervisor of
management mahmood I there are
11 eyes without objection
resolutions are adopted and the
motion is approved and then
MADAM Clerk we go to item 37.
>> item 37 this is a resolution
to reaffirm san francisco's
commitment to the
administrative code chapter 14
be local business enterprise
program supervisor welcome.
Thank you so much PRESIDENT
Mellman and colleagues, I just
wanted to thank all the
co-sponsors of the resolution
supervisors mound of men chan
mahmud dorsi and gaudio sauder
and melgar for your
co-sponsorship and I just want
to shout out to our L.B. And
our labor community for coming
together in their work and
supporting this.
Thank you.
And I think that is it.
We can take this item same
house with the same call
without objection the
resolution is adopted.
MADAM Clerk are do we have any
imperative agenda items?
>> no imperatives to report.
MR. PRESIDENT, could you read
our in memoriam?
>> yes.
Today's meeting will be
adjourned in memory of the
following beloved individuals
on behalf of PRESIDENT
Randleman for the late david
sir hagan and restauranteur
charles fan and on behalf of
supervisor mahmood for the late
mark israel.
And I think that brings us to
the end of our agenda MADAM
Clerk is there any further
business before us today?
>> that concludes our business
for today.
Thank you, MADAM Clerk.
>> as there is no further